okay welcome to uh episode three of the
BNB uh
connection uh with me is Brad shonfeld
um we're expanding our techn
technological repertoire here and using
our new HD cameras that we just bought
so um we're all proud of ourselves for
figuring this out so this episode is
going to be on periodization and this is
something that Brad and I sort of AG
agree with and sort of don't agree with
with but we've never
really duked it out uh so we want to we
want to talk about periodization here so
uh let's get start started um for those
who haven't listened to previous B&B
connections we just do 30 minute talks
about whatever's on our mind we try to
stick to one topic so we've got 29 more
minutes this one's on periodization Brad
what is
periodization um simp stated
periodization is the planned
manipulation of program variables to
bring about a given Fitness uh goal or a
given Fitness outcome and simply stated
it means that you uh when we talk about
program variables there sets reps uh
sort of the volume of training um and
that includes frequency and you can
throw in things like
um the speed of repetitions can be
periodized and really any program
variable anything that has to do with
talking resistance training here
specifically you can you can periodize
endurance training as well but you
manipulate them always the and I think
what kind of gets lost in some people
really the goal is to continue um to
allow for continued progress without
overtraining or or overtraining might
even be a uh a misnomer here it's really
um nonfunctional overreaching cuz
overtraining is a real more severe
aspect of
that okay so uh there I just turned the
light on um so netization is just
planning is that am I overly simplify if
I just say planning um well it's
planning in a way that yeah you're
oversimplifying in the sense that it's
planning in a way that will bring about
you can plan you can have bad plans so
it's the the plan is to uh is basically
Al not to keep pushing hard hard hard
all the time so it's to allow for uh
ultimately if you're looking at what my
concept of periodization is it's to plan
for having unloading periods so that
your training uh basically continues on
an upward Trend overall without
regressing on the on long term but you
do you have to unload to do
computerization be just hey I'm going to
focus on like here here here's my thing
and like I don't like most definitions
of periodization or most
people's understanding of it because
most people think of periodization they
just think of like Western linear
periodization they think of undulating
they think of these different models of
periodization and you think of the
charts where you see these you know
zigzagging things and things like
that but periodization could also just
be like okay I'm a personal trainer I
just got this beginner and they at
squats they don't have good ankle
Mobility they don't use their glutes
when they glute bridge and they can't
hip hinge and so my first month I'm
going to really focus on quality instead
of quantity Brad zoom out your camera
just automatically zoomed in
mind and
uh real quick you can see the difference
between a New Yorker see Brad being pale
white and see my nice Tan in Arizona
here just one reason why Arizona trumps
that is this is my Eastern European skin
and that is your Mexican skin so just
one reason why arizonian arizonians are
superior to New Yorkers but uh um anyway
um like so that could be a form of
intermingle enough that was the problem
so I got this pasty skin so that's
periodization right I'm a personal
trainer I say look this first month
we're going quality not quantity they're
going to do focus on glute activation
they're going to focus on hip hinging
they're going to focus on you know I'm
not going to worry about load I'm really
going to get their form looking good and
then you know next month I'll start to
load them up more and be concerned with
Progressive overload or something like
that can you what if you have a new goal
in mind hey I I want to try to really
focus on my squat this
month uh rather than my deadlift or
something or the just doing a different
program is a form of periodization
you're doing it's a different you're
just switching focuses switching
priorities so I will argue that you
can't it's pretty hard to not period
periodize like to not period periodize
you just have to you you would have to
go to the gym with no goal in mind and
just train aimlessly and do completely
different things and not care about
because almost everyone has goals and
they say I want my bench to go up or I
want this to go up so you're trying but
I will say most people don't period
periodize enough they don't have any
sort of Rhyme or Reason to their
training um I would say the majority of
people who train just go to the gym and
they do body part splits and they you
know you'll ask a lot of people what do
you do for your bench press oh I do 135
for 15 then I do 185 for 10 then I do
205 for six and then 225 for like two or
three and then I might do a back off set
of 115 for 15 reps and I'm like you do
that every time you go to the gym and
they're like yeah and I'm like would you
ever go up do you ever increase your
reps no and then other times uh I'll say
like you know what do you do for what do
you do for chest and they'll say well
I'll just kind of go in and pick like
three or four exercises sometimes I
might do crossovers then bench press
then
push-ups um then the next time I might
do dips and then close grip bench and
then
flies you know what I mean and then
there's know there's it's like okay
you're just doing complete muscle
confusion without even trying to get
better at one thing so those would be
two instances of really poor or a lack
of
periodization and uh studies show that
people who periodize see better results
than people who do not
correct um not
exactly uh the the actually the
literature is very conflicting on it uh
and really the here's the issue with the
period literature there are a gazillion
different ways to periodize there's no
periodization is really a concept so if
you do a let's say you do a research
study you're GNA the researcher has his
own model okay I'm going to do this
particular thing today and I'm going to
take it with a standard type of program
that doesn't change up any variables but
that's just one potential way to do
something and there are literally a
gazillion so really that's part of the
problem is that there is no such
periodization is really just the general
concept and so I think we're in
agreement that planning is the essence
of it and one of my favorite real quick
let's let's uh let's talk about the
variables I wish I had thought about
this beforeand had written them down but
what are the variables you can Tinker
with we've got the main ones are volume
intensity and frequency volume and
intensity are the most commonly
periodized but there's also frequency
frequ on hold on hold on frequency is
part of volume really yeah I within a
because if you you can let's say have if
you add an extra day and keep the volume
the same you you've increased volume for
that week so but but there's also
training frequency number of days and
then training frequency number of times
you hit a muscle or a lift so it's it's
that kind of like intensity that we
talked about last episode there's
intensity of effort and intensity of
load um frequency is kind of two things
too the frequency of true day days you
train and then frequency of the number
of times you hit a muscle or or or or
movement um so volume intensity but
intensity is two things frequency is two
things uh then there's Tempo you
could you can periodize intensity of
effort yeah so we so there's volume
there's intensity of effort intensity of
load frequency of training frequency of
times you hit a a muscle or movement um
Tempo yep Tempo uh or Cadence or Tempo
there's density trying to get in more in
a less time there's
uh would you say would you say variety
would be like variety would definitely
be a type of periodization yeah um you
could what else is there there's
uh
um probably probably more were foret the
use of yeah well I mean the use of other
specialized techniques y yep that's what
I was thinking of like doing drop drop
heavy negatives yeah right right
Ecentric accentuated or something
isometrics things like that but the most
uh the most common what would you say
the most common forms of periodization
are common forms well linear and
nonlinear are the two you're talking
about yeah the
model your two Basics are linear and
nonlinear yeah but but I I do want to
point out and I you're the thing you
said at the beginning that to me one of
my favorite phrases and I think most
important adages with training is those
who fail to plan plan to fail so if you
just go into the gym and and planning is
an really is at the heart of
periodization you just going into the
gym and saying I think I'm going to do
this today I think I'm GNA do without
having a real goal as to why you're
doing it uh you're destined to not get
good results and what periodization
really tries to do is to find a way to
systematize this uh and how you go about
it we can argue I know there's all sorts
of things in the literature is
undulating better than linear and I mean
to me that's kind of missing the boat
because there's no s there's a million
different ways to do linear
periodization and a million different
ways to do undulating there's so many
different but I think it's good for
researchers to try to pit two
periodization programs against each
other and see which one works better
well I I don't disagree but what is that
really that just tells you that that
particular periodization scheme that
that used was if something's done 10
times and you see that linear always
beats you know beats out whatever
nonlinear or something like that uh then
you could start to say okay I'm pretty
confident about this but well hold on
well here's the other thing you have to
look at though the study is almost
invariably a short-term in nature and
again to me what one of the real
important aspects of periodization is is
to uh prevent overtraining so really
it's planning but doing it in a way that
where I do think that some type of
unloading or or some or not structuring
it so that you're not always going balls
to the wall that you're allowing some
type of um variation in there so that
you have downtime in some way and that
you're not um pushing it constantly is
essential and if you're doing a 12-week
study you're not allowing enough time
for any of those factors to take place
so it's it's really not going to show up
in something like that you just you have
to have when we're looking at periodized
routines we'd be looking looking at the
effects over months you're talking three
six months really or more uh not not a
eight or 12 week routine there's not
much you can see and that's what really
most of what the research looks at just
because it's hard to do a very difficult
to do with three certainly a six-month
training study is is a very difficult
thing to accomplish really when you're
going out past three months you you
don't get many studies that do that just
because of the time the cost time
intensive nature and the cost of it so
that's a great point it's very very hard
to look at periodization in the research
due to the time constraints
um I have seen studies like on football
players and stuff looking at year one
year two but they don't control any
variable well they don't always but uh
okay so you pointed out a good Pitfall
um now let's talk about uh some things
about periodization like I think the
main my main thing um
is that first of all it's important to
note that a lot of
times people don't set records on like
it's different with strength training
versus Athletics versus so if you're
just a lifter like John Bros will tell
you that the body you know what you feel
is a lie and well I don't think he means
just ignore all everything your body
says it just means that you can't it's
unbelievable how many times you feel
like crap but set a record or you feel
great and perform like crap so that's um
it's very hard to predict human
physiology
and human physiology is so um dependent
on so many factors for you to nail an
event I mean look at sprinters you know
they need to Peak once every four years
from the Olympics and they don't they
rarely do it uh it's a very with
sprinting is probably the one end of the
extreme you know but for most people
they're just general lifters do General
lifters
uh I I agree that periodizing is a
better approach I agree that you should
map out a plan I agree that you should
say all right here's what I'm going to
do and I'm a fan of competing pick a
powerlifting competition or a
bodybuilding competition or something
that forces you to Peak or just say I'm
going to do a mock meat on this day or
do a photo shoot on this day because it
holds you accountable you you then Peak
for this and and people who Peak and who
compete see better results because they
push it they're really focused they push
it really hard and then afterwards you
kind of relax chill out you're on the
offseason a little bit and then you get
refocused so it's these natural times of
intenser training and less intense
training but uh I I totally agree that
you get better results by periodizing
but I will tell you I can't be I can't
believe how many you know having a lot
of powerlifting friends and
I thought you know in the last couple
years that I've made I thought I thought
the difference would be that you get
these newbies and they just suck at
their training they don't periodize they
they they they're program Hoppers they
jump ship the second a new program comes
out they try to combine programs they do
three programs at once there's no Rhyme
or Reason to their training they're just
idiotic with their training but I see
the same thing with a lot of
powerlifters they do make the same
mistakes that other that normal people
do it's just that they're genetically
Superior they're just built to be
stronger but I hold on hold on so the
thing I think you're missing there
though that doesn't mean there might be
powerlifters that doesn't mean they
might not be getting better results if
they plan right so
that's the question I wanted to ask you
is how much better so you get these um I
will tell you there's worldclass
powerlifters who you know I I was
reading about a guy who um has squat
natural squat record I forgot his name
maybe it's like Rob Wilkinson or
something he's I don't know if he has a
record but he's this big giant uh black
guy that just legs like a tree trunk and
he in an interview he said he doesn't
even really know what he's going to do
when he goes in he doesn't even have a
plan really he just but he's going to
squat you
know uh and I and I see so many examples
of guys who you know they just know
they're going to be training a few they
don't really know what they're going to
do when they go in but they do have a
general framework so here's my whole
point in the beginning was they you
might think those guys don't have a
system but they do have a system because
they know what they can Squat and
they're trying to beat it and if they
feel like it um this tiny meager he's
got the strongest um shirted bench in
the world and he goes in uh to to to
bench and he only like maybe once a
month goes for a record he once a month
tries to really go heavy depending on
how he feels because he's bench and like
whatever it is like 1100 lb or whatever
he can't if he feels off he'll hurt
something so you can have a plan but if
you you've got to have some flexibility
in there which is Mel would call
cybernetic periodization or Auto
regulation or some people just call it
listening to biof feedback but that's
what I would like to talk about two
things first of all how important is uh
how much better is it I mean is it like
if you don't have a if you don't
periodize properly you're going to see
Zero results versus if you do periodize
you're going to see 100% results or is
it more like you can get just 15% more
gains when you have a good plan I mean
that's that's my take is kind of
like it helps to periodize but it's
there are lots of lifters who have good
results when they don't proper they
don't follow proper strict protocols
completely agree and you can there
there's so many people that uh train
terribly and see very good results in
terms they they see impressive results
that doesn't mean they couldn't see
better so I think look it depends number
one how halfhazard your training is if
you just have a terrible routine you're
still can see some results but you'll
see poor results and you the better you
plan ultimately the better your results
but I here's a couple of um just to go
on what you said number one I think
having some type of Auto regulatory uh
approach is really important cuz if
you're feeling bad and you just are
pushing you're not only you're not going
to get uh the right results out of what
you're doing it's going to screw things
up but you can even push yourself
towards overtraining or or do
non-functional overreaching in that type
of context um but just as importantly I
don't think we the I think the other
side is we shouldn't look at the
nonlinear linear in such a strict
fashion that really we want to just look
at planning and how you go about it I
think the approach that you ultimately
take needs to be based on what your
goals are I think personally I think if
you need you want to Peak for a certain
event then taking a more linear type
approach makes sense and if you're
looking like in team sports Etc where
you're looking just to get overall
results over the course of a period of
time an undulating approach tends to
make more sense and there's hybrid
approaches within that so there's not I
think that's another problem with when
we talk about this we we get very caught
up in these type of models if if you
will and I think that that's really the
wrong way to look at it that the
periodization again is just a concept
it's a planning concept and how we go
about doing it is very individual and
and needs to take in the auto regulatory
aspects and you look at all these
popular systems out there uh look at bro
John bro's approach they train to a Max
every day but it's a competition Max
it's they go by how they feel you don't
force a a a PR if it's not there it's a
competition Max but there is some
structure to the program they're going
to be doing the six lifts the squat the
front squat the clean uh or the clean
and jerk the snatch the power snatch and
the and the power clean but uh they have
a rigid you know these are the times
they do their lifts and this is how the
the work schedule is planned out
throughout the week but you don't really
know what weights you're going to hit
you just know that over time every 6
months you want to be using
greater loads than you were the previous
6 months there is a model built upon
effort and work you look at West Side
they're going to max out 52 weeks out of
the year they go heavy but they rotate
the maximal effort lifts it's either a
heavy good morning or a heavy box
squat uh seldomly a heavy deadlift they
do Dynamic effort stuff they do their
assistance lifts they have it dialed in
for um geared training because the
powerlifting gear gives you the
assistance at the bottom and you need to
lock it out so they do tons of you know
um stuff that's going to help their lock
out but I think they've got a and and
they do Dynamic effort stuff so it
doesn't beat the crap out of them so
they're doing explosive work and I think
they've got an amazing system but it's
not rigid they're they're going to try
to max out every week on things whether
they get it or not they don't really
know but then you've got other systems
like you
know Chico you use strict percentages
you know and some systems are based on
you know you have your one rep max and
you're going to use you know 60% of your
one rep max and you're going to do these
many sets and Reps and the next week
you're going to do this and then you've
got like 531 gy one there's
531 but on your last set you if you can
get more you get more so you you aren't
like so that's a good little mechanism
there for increasing the intensity
because the intensity of effort because
if you just stopped at one you know but
you could get five you should probably
push the envelope and get five you're
going to induce a better training
stimulus but then there are other
systems that are they keep you they
prevent you from overreaching from
overtraining because they do hold you
back and like I sometimes when I train
my my clients I know they could set a PR
I know they could I could I can tell cuz
they just they just you can just tell
they they just set a three rep max
record or whatever they look explosive
that day but I let them I let it ride
till the next week because I don't want
them you know uh expending all their I
want to you want it like a steamroller
you know it's hard to get a steamroller
in motion but it's hard to stop it once
it's in motion you want to build up
momentum and keep riding that momentum
rather than just you know be greedy get
all your gains and then not have
anything left well here's here's another
that I would say as far as um
periodizing if you are looking to Peak
for a certain event I train a lot of
physique competitors
bodybuilders uh figure type athletes and
um if you are looking to let's say for a
given competition looking to have them
Peak to me I I found the best results in
pushing them towards a period of
functional overreaching where you have
you create greater density over time now
if you just create you just keep pushing
the envelope pushing the en envelope
ultimately they're going to be dead
they're G dead they're going to be
overtrained dead from a competitive
standpoint by the time your the
competition is over the course of time
so you have to do it in a structured
systematic fashion but then uh plan it
so that the the actual overreaching will
take place in and around right before
that competitive event and that is so
important that's why if you're just
pushing the envelope pushing the
envelope by the time you're competing
you you can't really get to a functional
overreaching standpoint you're you're
either non-functionally overreached
which is basically overtrained uh or you
don't get to you don't get that density
and you basically fall short of that so
I think that is a really important uh
facet in terms of periodizing to to plan
it out if you're going to have such an
event that your your uh training is D is
really dense and and very especially
from a volume standpoint really um
heighten volume right before for that
competition and then you have your D
Lo yep so I like to think of it a lot of
times like you know I have my it you can
set up your weekly schedule however you
want you can lift one day a week two
days a week three days four five six
7even days a week and there's ways to
make it work for every one of those but
I like an approach I like is I
like getting my I like having Sunday off
and sometimes I'll take Saturday off but
I like feeling a little bit beat down by
the end of the week and then I I eat big
over the weekend I rest and then I come
back the next week ready to roll again
and it then the process repeats and
that's functional overreaching because I
come back stronger but if I didn't come
back stronger it's not um you're not
doing it right um but some things I want
to talk about we've got five minutes
left in the
literature tell me if you'd agree with
this Brad because I've got like 50
papers on periodization linear
periodization can work very well a lot
of people think that it doesn't yep um I
would say out of the studies given what
your goal is again right right
periodization really it's the focus of
it and it was developed towards Olympic
type uh towards Olympic events where
you're going to Peak at a certain period
uh if you're if you're doing a um sport
specific type of thing the undulating
approach I you let's say you're a
baseball player and you're peing right
before the season then you're trying to
maintain during the season you're
getting worn down during the season so
I'm not personally I think a lot of
times for many of the team sports that
the undulating approach is a better uh
way to go that's a good point with
sports that have frequent games a lot of
these models go out the window because
you can't you're not peeking them and um
you're not maintain you can Peak but
then you don't maintain it's very
difficult to maintain it time tell a lot
of my coach friends you know like
depending on the if they've got freshman
football players sophomores they build
strength throughout the season because
they're young they're immature they're
not they haven't been training properly
so that's a misnomer that you can't
build strength during season in sports
um but uh but you would want to reduce
volume to account for the more games
that you're playing um in the literature
when I see that I would give the edge
when linear is is uh pitted against uh
like daily undulating periodization I
would give the a edge to daily
undulating periodization I've personally
the studies I have I've seen more of
that but again like you say they're
shorter studies they're eight 8 to 12
weeks or so I would also say that when
Auto regulatory training is incorporated
into the mix that leads to better
results and um there's amazingly complex
per ation models and books written on it
and then there's great researchers who
have critiqued those models um like
iserin um um what is the guy's name
uh have have to one of the best books on
periodization what I really like about
their book uh they use the step loading
they discuss step loading and in depth
and that to me is a very important
aspect of cre kind of a wave like I
think it's important to have these you
say BM yeah t to baa and Greg half um a
great job it's called periodization in
the book yep so there's lots of good
systems but I guess what I want to end
with is two my two main takeaway points
with
periodization uh number one for the
because I think a lot of personal
trainers and strength coaches watch our
stuff Brad so for what I want to
conclude with is you're probably period
periodizing
your stuff whether you know it or not
you're probably doing a good job of it
so be confident in that number two you
don't have to have this crazy knowledge
of it might benefit you as a trainer a
coach to learn these different
models but I have had great success just
kind of winging it I know what I want my
athletes and clients to do I know what
my goals are but I don't have strict
guidelines like today they're going to
do this I don't write out their programs
two months in advance I go by what I see
and what I feel but I know what I want
to achieve and you can see really good
results that way um not to say you
couldn't see better results if you were
more structured but just saying don't
feel bad if you don't have all these
periodization models down pat and number
three listen to biof feedback that is
such a critical component to uh good
program design because you can never
predict how the body will feel and
perform and you have to be ready to
adjust any program on paper is just a a
guideline you have to adjust depending
on how you feel you some days you push
it it's kind of like that Kenny Rogers
song you got to know when to hold them
know when to fold them know when to walk
away and know when to run and by the way
I would also point out when we talked
about unloading that I would say the
majority of people don't train hard
enough to need unloading periods so you
know when I'm working with a bodybuilder
or a figure competitor these are people
that are really at the top of their
Sports and they're pushing themselves
and those are the people are certainly
athletes uh even some of the hard
training recreational athletes sometimes
but most people I mean as a trainer 80%
of the people I work with never would
train consistently hard enough where
youd need that you basically their their
unloading was built into the types of
training a Great point I always say
there's overtraining there's also under
trining and most people and there's
getting it just right and like I like to
think that I've gotten to a point where
I know my training just right I don't
overtrain I don't under Trin and uh but
we've got 30 minutes and 30 seconds now
so we are done here Bradley thank you
very much this is uh hopefully this all
works when I transfer it to uh YouTube's
to the interwebs but uh thank you
Bradley as always and we will be back
next week we don't know what the topic
will be but we'll figure something out
thanks for watching later guys